Introduction

The novel <PERSON>Jane Eyre</PERSON> is a first-person narrative of the title character. The novel is set somewhere in the north of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, during the reign of <PERSON>George III</PERSON> (1760-1820), and goes through five distinct stages: <PERSON>Jane</PERSON>'s childhood at <LOCATION>Gateshead Hall</LOCATION>, where she is emotionally and physically abused by her aunt and cousins; her education at <LOCATION>Lowood School</LOCATION>, where she acquires friends and role models but suffers privations and oppression; her time as governess at <LOCATION>Thornfield Hall</LOCATION>, where she falls in love with her Byronic employer, <PERSON>Edward Rochester</PERSON>; her time with the Rivers family, during which her earnest but cold clergyman cousin, St. <PERSON>John Rivers</PERSON>, proposes to her; and her reunion with, and marriage to, her beloved <LOCATION>Rochester</LOCATION>. During these sections the novel provides perspectives on a number of important social issues and ideas, many of which are critical of the status quo (see the Themes section below). Literary critic <PERSON>Jerome Beaty</PERSON> opines that the close first person perspective leaves the reader "too uncritically accepting of her worldview", and often leads reading and conversation about the novel towards supporting <PERSON>Jane</PERSON>, regardless of how irregular her ideas or perspectives are.[5]

<PERSON>Jane Eyre</PERSON> is divided into 38 chapters, and most editions are at least 400 pages long. The original publication was in three volumes, 
comprising chapters 1 to 15, 16 to 26, and 27 to 38; this was a common publishing format during the 19th century (see three-volume novel).

<PERSON>Brontë</PERSON> dedicated the novel's second edition to <PERSON>William Makepeace Thackeray</PERSON>.

<PERSON>Jane</PERSON>'s childhood
Young <PERSON>Jane</PERSON> argues with her guardian Mrs. <PERSON>Reed</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Gateshead</LOCATION>, illustrated by <PERSON>F. H. Townsend</PERSON>

The novel begins with the titular character, <PERSON>Jane Eyre</PERSON>, aged 10, living with her maternal uncle's family, the Reeds, as a result of her uncle's dying wish. It is several years after her parents died of typhus. Mr. <PERSON>Reed</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jane</PERSON>'s uncle, was the only one in the <PERSON>Reed</PERSON> family who was kind to <PERSON>Jane</PERSON>. <PERSON>Jane</PERSON>'s aunt, <PERSON>Sarah Reed</PERSON>, dislikes her, treats her as a burden, and discourages her children from associating with <PERSON>Jane</PERSON>. Mrs. <PERSON>Reed</PERSON> and her three children are abusive to <PERSON>Jane</PERSON>, physically, emotionally, and, as the reader is quick to realize, spiritually. The nursemaid <PERSON>Bessie</PERSON> proves to be <PERSON>Jane</PERSON>'s only ally in the household, even though <PERSON>Bessie</PERSON> sometimes harshly scolds <PERSON>Jane</PERSON>. Excluded from the family activities, <PERSON>Jane</PERSON> is incredibly unhappy, with only a doll and books in which to find solace.

One day, after her cousin <PERSON>John</PERSON> knocks her down and she attempts to defend herself, <PERSON>Jane</PERSON> is locked in the red room where her uncle died; there, she faints from panic after she thinks she has seen his ghost. She is subsequently attended to by the kindly apothecary, Mr. <PERSON>Lloyd</PERSON>, to whom <PERSON>Jane</PERSON> reveals how unhappy she is living at <LOCATION>Gateshead Hall</LOCATION>. He recommends to Mrs. <PERSON>Reed</PERSON> that <PERSON>Jane</PERSON> should be sent to school, an idea Mrs. <PERSON>Reed</PERSON> happily supports. Mrs. <PERSON>Reed</PERSON> then enlists the aid of the harsh Mr. <PERSON>Brocklehurst</PERSON>, director of <ORGANIZATION>Lowood Institution</ORGANIZATION>, a charity school for girls. Mrs. <PERSON>Reed</PERSON> cautions Mr. <PERSON>Brocklehurst</PERSON> that <PERSON>Jane</PERSON> has a "tendency for deceit", which he interprets as her being a "liar". Before <PERSON>Jane</PERSON> leaves, however, she confronts Mrs. <PERSON>Reed</PERSON> and declares that she'll never call her "aunt" again, that Mrs. <PERSON>Reed</PERSON> and her daughter, <PERSON>Georgana</PERSON>, are the ones who are deceitful, and that she'll tell everyone at <LOCATION>Lowood</LOCATION> how cruelly Mrs. <PERSON>Reed</PERSON> treated her.[6]

<PERSON>Lowood</PERSON>

At <ORGANIZATION>Lowood Institution</ORGANIZATION>, a school for poor and orphaned girls, <PERSON>Jane</PERSON> soon finds that life is harsh, but she attempts to fit in and befriends an older girl, <PERSON>Helen Burns</PERSON>, who is able to accept her punishment philosophically. During a school inspection by Mr. <PERSON>Brocklehurst</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jane</PERSON> accidentally breaks her slate, thereby drawing attention to herself. He then stands her on a stool, brands her a liar, and shames her before the entire assembly. <PERSON>Jane</PERSON> is later comforted by her friend, <PERSON>Helen</PERSON>. Miss Temple, the caring superintendent, facilitates <PERSON>Jane</PERSON>'s self-defence and writes to Mr. <PERSON>Lloyd</PERSON>, whose reply agrees with <PERSON>Jane</PERSON>'s. <PERSON>Jane</PERSON> is then publicly cleared of Mr. <PERSON>Brocklehurst</PERSON>'s accusations.

The 80 pupils at <LOCATION>Lowood</LOCATION> are subjected to cold rooms, poor meals, and thin clothing. Many students fall ill when a typhus epidemic strikes, and <PERSON>Jane</PERSON>'s friend <PERSON>Helen</PERSON> dies of consumption in her arms. When Mr. <PERSON>Brocklehurst</PERSON>'s maltreatment of the students is discovered, several benefactors erect a new building and install a sympathetic management committee to moderate Mr. <PERSON>Brocklehurst</PERSON>'s harsh rule. Conditons at the school then improve dramatically.

The name <PERSON>Lowood</PERSON> symbolizes the "low" point in <PERSON>Jane</PERSON>'s life where she was maltreated. <PERSON>Helen Burns</PERSON> is a representation of <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>'s elder 
sister <PERSON>Maria</PERSON>, who died of tuberculosis after spending time at a school where the children were mistreated.